A Guide to the Papers Pertaining to Middle East Ventures of the Mobil Oil Corporation, 1951-1960
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Papers Pertaining to Middle East Ventures of the Mobil Oil Corporation, 1951-1960
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
11224
This collection consists of 25,000 items (50 Hollinger boxes, ca. 28 linear shelf feet).
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
These papers were loaned to the University of Virginia Library by the Mobil Oil Corporation, Fairfax, Virginia, on March 11, 1996.
Scope and Content Information
This collection consists of ca. 25,000 items, ca. 1951-1960, the papers of Mobil Oil Corporation and its Middle East petroleum ventures, filed under the headings of personnel, organization, conventions, supplies, pipelines, legal matters, prices, production, agreements, finances, meetings, office, agreements, reports, and government. The folders have an additional subheading depending on the name of the oil company involved.
These papers cover the period of the greatest expansion of oil companies and their influence in the Middle East before countries like Iraq and Iran nationalized their oil industries. Topics mentioned in the papers include: the Suez Canal Crisis in 1956, which closed the canal for four months and drastically affected some oil exports; the purchase of Safaniya crude oil & the Ras Tanura Refinery, and other crude oil under the heading agreements; Under the heading of conventions and pipelines, there is a file on Tapline, the TransArabian Pipeline Company, which opened in December 1950 as the world's largest crude oil pipeline providing an outlet on the Mediterranean Sea for crude oil from ARAMCO's producing fields destined for Europe.
In 1933, the key oil concession in Saudi Arabia was assigned to California Arabian Standard Oil Company, which rose to international prominence during World War II when the U.S. government encouraged rapid development and full production for the war effort. The name of the company was changed in 1944 to Arabian American Oil Company or ARAMCO and by 1947 the Texas Company, Standard Oil Company of New Jersey, and Socony Vacuum Oil Company had all become partners in the Middle East venture, making ARAMCO the world's most important oil cartel.
Other oil companies represented in this collection include the British Petroleum Company, registered in 1909 as the Anglo-Persian Oil Company, Ltd., renamed the Anglo- Iranian Oil Company, Ltd., in 1935 and becoming the British Petroleum Company Limited in 1954, formed to take over and finance an oil-field concession in Iran; the Iranian Oil Participants, Ltd., a consortium of fourteen oil companies producing oil in Iran; the Iraq Petroleum Company, Ltd., a consortium of oil companies in Iraq; and Mobil Oil.
The origins of Mobil Oil Corporation date to the 19th century. According to the Encyclopedia Britannica, "One predecessor, Vacuum Oil Company, was founded in 1866 and, after 1882, became part of the Standard Oil Trust. Another predecessor was Standard Oil Company of New York (Socony), established by the trust in 1882. Both companies became independent in 1911 when the U.S. Supreme Court dissolved the Standard Oil combine, but the two merged in 1931 to form Socony-Vacuum Corporation. The name was changed in 1934 to Socony-Vacuum Oil Company, Inc., in 1955 to Socony Mobil Oil Company, Inc., and then in 1966 to Mobil Oil Corporation."
Arrangement
This collection consists of ca. 25,000 items (50 Hollinger boxes, ca. 28 linear shelf feet), ca. 1951-1960, the papers of Mobil Oil Corporation and its Middle East petroleum ventures, filed under the headings of personnel, organization, conventions, supplies, pipelines, legal matters, prices, production, agreements, finances, meetings, office, agreements, reports, and government. The folders have an additional subheading depending on the name of the oil company involved.
Contents List
- Agreements - Arabian American Oil Company - Offtake Agreements ca. 1956-1957, 4 folders (Box 1)
- Agreements - Arabian American Oil Company - Offtake Agreements ca. 1958-1959, 4 folders (Box 1)
- Agreements - Arabian American Oil Company - Offtake Agreements ca. 1959 Jul-1960, 3 of 4 folders (Box 1)
- Agreements - Arabian American Oil Company - Offtake Agreements ca. 1959 Jul-1960, 4 of 4 folders (Box 2)
- Agreements - British Petroleum Company, Ltd. - First Purchases ca. 1956-1957, 5 folders (Box 2)
- Agreements - British Petroleum Company, Ltd. - First Purchases ca. 1958-1959, 5 folders (Box 2)
- Agreements - British Petroleum Company, Ltd. - Heads of Agreement ca. 1955-1959, 6 folders (Box 3)
- Agreements - British Petroleum Company, Ltd. - Second Purchase ca. 1951-1957, 4 folders (Box 3)
- Agreements - Iranian Oil Participants, Ltd. - Offtake Agreements ca. 1955-1956, 4 folders (Box 4)
- Agreements - Iranian Oil Participants, Ltd. - Offtake Agreements ca. 1957, 3 folders (Box 4)
- Agreements - Iraq Petroleum Co. Ltd - Inter-Group Agreements ca. 1955-1957, 3 folders (Box 5)
- Agreements - Iraq Petroleum Co. Ltd - Sale Of Oil Agreement ca. 1951-1956, 3 folders (Box 5)
- Agreements - Mobil Oil Company Qatar ca. 1955-1959, 2 folders (Box 5)
- Agreements - Mobil Oil Iraq, Ltd ca.1954-1956, 1 of 4 folders (Box 5)
- Agreements - Mobil Oil Iraq, Ltd ca.1954-1956, 3 of 4 folders (Box 6)
- Arabian American Oil Company ca.1955-1959, 4 folders (Box 6)
- Conventions - Arabian American Oil Company ca.1956 Jan-Jul, 3 of 4 folders (Box 6)
- Conventions - Arabian American Oil Company ca.1956 Jan-Jul, 4 of 4 folders (Box 7)
- Conventions - Arabian American Oil Company ca.1956 Aug-1957 Mar., 5 folders (Box 7)
- Conventions - Arabian American Oil Company ca.1957 Apr-Oct, 4 folders (Box 7)
- Conventions - Iraq Petroleum Co. Ltd - Iraq ca.1951-1952, 4 folders (Box 8)
- Conventions - Iraq Petroleum Co. Ltd - Iraq ca.1953-1954, 3 folders (Box 8)
- Conventions - Iraq Petroleum Co. Ltd - Iraq ca.1955, 3 folders (Box 8)
- Conventions - Iraq Petroleum Co. Ltd - Iraq ca.1956, 3 folders (Box 9)
- Conventions - Iraq Petroleum Co. Ltd - Lebanon ca.1955-1956 Feb., 2 folders (Box 9)
- Conventions - Iraq Petroleum Co. Ltd - Lebanon ca.1956 Mar-Aug, 5 folders (Box 9)
- Conventions - Iraq Petroleum Co. Ltd - Lebanon ca.1956 Sept-Dec, 4 folders (Box 10)
- Conventions - Iraq Petroleum Co. Ltd - Syria And Lebanon ca.1951-1952, 5 folders (Box 10)
- Conventions - Iraq Petroleum Co. Ltd - Syria And Lebanon ca.1953-1954 Mar, 2 of 4 folders (Box 10)
- Conventions - Iraq Petroleum Co. Ltd - Syria And Lebanon ca.1953-1954 Mar, 2 of 4 folders (Box 11)
- Conventions - Iraq Petroleum Co. Ltd - Syria And Lebanon ca.1954 Apr-1955 Aug, 4 folders (Box 11)
- Conventions - Iraq Petroleum Co. Ltd - Syria And Lebanon ca.1955 Sept-Oct, 3 folders (Box 11)
- Conventions - Iraq Petroleum Co. Ltd - Syria And Lebanon ca.1955 Nov-Dec 14, 1 of 5 folders (Box 11)
- Conventions - Iraq Petroleum Co. Ltd - Syria And Lebanon ca.1955 Nov-Dec 14, 4 of 5 folders (Box 12)
- Conventions - Iraq Petroleum Co. Ltd - Qatar ca.1951-1953, 4 folders (Box 12)
- Conventions - Iraq Petroleum Co. Ltd - Qatar ca.1954-1955, 2 folders (Box 12)
- Conventions - Iraq Petroleum Co. Ltd - Qatar ca.1956-1958, 3 folders (Box 13)
- Conventions - Tapline ca.1951-1956 Jul, 4 folders (Box 13)
- Conventions - Tapline ca.1956 Aug-1957 Apr, 3 of 5 folders (Box 13)
- Conventions - Tapline ca.1956 Aug-1957 Apr, 2 of 5 folders (Box 14)
- Conventions - Tapline ca.1957 May-Dec, 3 folders (Box 14)
- Conventions - Tapline - Drafts ca.1957-1958, 2 folders (Box 14)
- Financial - Arabian American Oil Company - General ca.1956, 2 of 4 folders (Box 14)
- Financial - Arabian American Oil Company - General ca.1956, 2 of 4 folders (Box 15)
- Financial - Arabian American Oil Company - General ca.1957, 7 folders (Box 15)
- Financial - Iraq Petroleum Co. Ltd ca.1956, 2 of 5 folders (Box 15)
- Financial - Iraq Petroleum Co. Ltd ca.1956, 3 of 5 folders (Box 16)
- Financial - Iraq Petroleum Co. Ltd - Balance Sheets ca.1957-1958, 5 folders (Box 16)
- Financial - Iraq Petroleum Co. Ltd - Balance Sheets ca.1959-1960, 2 of 4 folders (Box 16)
- Financial - Iraq Petroleum Co. Ltd - Balance Sheets ca.1959-1960, 2 of 4 folders (Box 17)
- Financial - Iraq Petroleum Co. Ltd - Balance Sheets ca.1960-1961, 3 folders (Box 17)
- Financial - Iraq Petroleum Co. Ltd - Balance Sheets ca.1962, 3 folders (Box 17)
- Financial - Iraq Petroleum Co. Ltd - Budget ca.1959 Jan-Jun, 2 folders (Box 17)
- Financial - Iraq Petroleum Co. Ltd - Budget ca.1959 Jul-Dec, 3 folders (Box 18)
- Financial - Iraq Petroleum Co. Ltd - General ca.1957, 4 folders (Box 18)
- Financial - Mobil Oil Iran ca.1954-1955 Feb, 3 of 4 folders (Box 18)
- Financial - Mobil Oil Iran ca.1954-1955 Feb, 4 of 4 folders (Box 19)
- Financial - Mobil Oil Iran ca.1955 Mar-Oct, 3 folders (Box 19)
- Financial - Mobil Oil Iran ca.1955 Nov-1956 Jun, 2 folders (Box 19)
- Financial - Mobil Oil Iran ca.1956 Jul-1957 Jun, 2 folders (Box 19)
- Financial - Mobil Oil Iran ca.1957 Jul-1958 Jun, 1 of 3 folders (Box 19)
- Financial - Mobil Oil Iran ca.1957 Jul-1958 Jun, 2 of 3 folders (Box 20)
- Financial - Mobil Oil Iraq ca.1955-1956 Jun, 3 folders (Box 20)
- Financial - Mobil Oil Iraq ca.1956 Jul-1957 Jun, 3 folders (Box 20)
- Financial - Mobil Oil Iraq ca.1957 Jul-1958, 2 of 3 folders (Box 20)
- Financial - Mobil Oil Iraq ca.1957 Jul-1958, 3 of 3 folders (Box 21)
- Financial - Mobil Oil Company Of Qatar ca.1955-1956 Jun, 3 folders (Box 21)
- Financial - Mobil Oil Company Of Qatar ca.1956 Jul-1957, 2 folders (Box 21)
- Financial - Socony Mobil Oil Company ca.1956, 4 folders (Box 21)
- Financial - Socony Mobil Oil Company ca.1957 Jan-Jun, 4 folders (Box 22)
- Financial - Socony Mobil Oil Company ca.1957 Jul-Dec, 3 folders (Box 22)
- Financial - Sovoil ca.1956-1957, 3 folders (Box 22)
- Government Agencies ca.1955-1959, 1 of 6 folders (Box 22)
- Government Agencies ca.1955-1959, 5 of 6 folders (Box 23)
- Government - Arabian American Oil Company - Agencies ca.1955-1957, 4 folders (Box 23)
- Government - General ca.1952-1957, 2 of 5 folders (Box 23)
- Government - General f ca.1952-1957, 3 of 5 folders (Box 24)
- Government - General ca.1958, 2 folders (Box 24)
- Government - Nationalization ca.1956-1957, ca.1956-1957 (Box 24)
- Government - Political Situations ca.1956, 5 folders (Box 24)
- Government - Political Situations ca.1957-1958, 4 folders (Box 25)
- Government - United Nations ca.1958-1959, 4 folders (Box 25)
- Legal Matters ca.1952-1957, 1 of 3 folders (Box 25)
- Legal Matters ca.1952-1957, 2 of 3 folders (Box 26)
- Meetings - Iranian Oil Participants,Ltd - Board Of Directors ca.1954-1955, 2 folders (Box 26)
- Meetings - Iranian Oil Participants,Ltd - Board Of Directors ca.1956, 4 folders (Box 26)
- Meetings - Iranian Oil Participants,Ltd - Board Of Directors ca.1957, 1 of 3 folders (Box 26)
- Meetings - Iranian Oil Participants,Ltd - Board Of Directors ca.1957, 2 of 3 folders (Box 27)
- Meetings - Iranian Oil Participants,Ltd - Miscellaneous ca.1954-1958, 4 folders (Box 27)
- Meetings - Iranian Oil Participants,Ltd - Operating Companies ca .1955-1956, 3 of 4 folders (Box 27)
- Meetings - Iranian Oil Participants,Ltd - Operating Companies ca.1955-1956, 4 of 4 folders (Box 28)
- Meetings - Iranian Oil Participants,Ltd - Operating Companies ca.1957-1959, 4 folders (Box 28)
- Meetings - Iranian Oil Services Limited - Board Of Directors ca.1954-1956, 3 folders (Box 28)
- Meetings - Iranian Oil Services Limited - Board Of Directors ca.1957-1959, 3 folders (Box 28)
- Office - General ca.1955-1956, 3 folders (Box 29)
- Office - General ca.1957-1959, 3 folders (Box 29)
- Organization - Arabian American Oil Company ca.1955-1958, 3 folders (Box 29)
- Organization - Iranian Oil Participants,Ltd ca.1954-1955, 3 folders (Box 30)
- Organization - Iranian Oil Participants,Ltd ca.1956-1958, 3 folders (Box 30)
- Organization - Iranian Oil Participants,Ltd - Additional Participation ca.1954-1955, 3 of 4 folders (Box 30)
- Organization - Iranian Oil Participants,Ltd - Additional Participation ca.1954-1955, 4 of 4 folders (Box 31)
- Personnel - Iranian Oil Participants,Ltd ca.1954-1955, 4 folders (Box 31)
- Personnel - Iranian Oil Participants,Ltd ca.1957, 3 folders (Box 31)
- Personnel - Iranian Oil Participants,Ltd And Iranian Oil Services Limited ca.1956, 2 folders (Box 32)
- Personnel - Iranian Oil Participants,Ltd And Iranian Oil Services Limited ca.1957, 3 folders (Box 32)
- Personnel - Iranian Oil Participants,Ltd And Iranian Oil Services Limited - Employment ca.1956, 3 of 4 folders (Box 32)
- Personnel - Iranian Oil Participants,Ltd And Iranian Oil Services Limited - Employment ca.1956, 4 of 4 folders (Box 33)
- Personnel - Iranian Oil Participants, Ltd - Pension ca.1954-1955, 3 folders (Box 33)
- Personnel - Iraq Petroleum Co. Ltd - Pension ca.1956, 2 folders (Box 33)
- Personnel - Iraq Petroleum Co. Ltd - Pension ca.1957, 2 of 3 folders (Box 33)
- Personnel - Iraq Petroleum Co. Ltd - Pension ca.1957, 3 of 3 folders (Box 34)
- Personnel - Iraq Petroleum Co. Ltd - Pension ca.1958, 3 folders (Box 34)
- Pipelines - Iranian Oil Participants, Ltd ca.1956-1958, 4 folders (Box 34)
- Pipelines Industry ca.1956-1957 Apr, 5 folders (Box 35)
- Pipelines Industry ca.1957 May-Jun, 3 folders (Box 35)
- Pipelines Industry ca.1957 Jul, 1 of 4 folders (Box 35)
- Pipelines Industry ca.1957 Jul, 3 of 4 folders (Box 36)
- Pipelines - Iraq Petroleum Co. Ltd ca.1955-1956, 4 folders (Box 36)
- Pipelines - Iraq Petroleum Co. Ltd ca.1957, 4 folders (Box 36)
- Pipelines - Iraq Petroleum Co. Ltd ca.1958, 3 folders (Box 37)
- Pipelines - Iraq Petroleum Co. Ltd - Basrah - Kuwait ca.1955-1957, 3 folders (Box 37)
- Pipelines - Iraq Petroleum Co. Ltd - Claim ca.1957-1960, 4 folders (Box 37)
- Pipelines - Tapline ca.1951-1956, 3 folders (Box 38)
- Prices - General ca.1955-1958, 4 folders (Box 38)
- Prices - Iraq Petroleum Co. Ltd ca.1955-1956, 3 of 4 folders (Box 38)
- Prices - Iraq Petroleum Co. Ltd ca.1955-1956, 4 of 4 folders (Box 39)
- Prices - Iraq Petroleum Co. Ltd ca.1957-1958, 5 folders (Box 39)
- Production ca.1955-1959, 4 folders (Box 39)
- Production-Arabian American Oil Company ca. 1947-1955, 3 folders (Box 40)
- Production-Arabian American Oil Company ca. 1955-1957, 3 folders (Box 40)
- Production - Iranian Oil Participants,Ltd ca.1954-1957, 3 folders (Box 40)
- Production - Iraq Petroleum Co. Ltd ca.1954-1955, 3 folders (Box 41)
- Production - Iraq Petroleum Co. Ltd ca.1956-1958, 4 folders (Box 41)
- Reports - Iranian Oil Participants, Ltd ca.1955-1956, 3 folders (Box 41)
- Reports - Iranian Oil Participants, Ltd ca.1957, 3 folders (Box 42)
- Reports - Iranian Oil Participants, Ltd ca.1958, 4 folders (Box 42)
- Reports - Iranian Oil Participants, Ltd - Operating Companies ca.1954-1955, 2 of 4 folders (Box 42)
- Reports - Iranian Oil Participants,Ltd - Operating Companies ca.1954-1955, 2 of 4 folders (Box 43)
- Reports - Iranian Oil Participants,Ltd - Operating Companies ca.1957, 3 folders (Box 43)
- Reports - Iranian Oil Services Limited ca.1955, 2 folders (Box 43)
- Reports - Iranian Oil Services Limited ca.1956, 2 folders (Box 43)
- Reports - Iranian Oil Services Limited ca.1957, 1 of 3 folders (Box 43)
- Reports - Iranian Oil Services Limited ca.1957, 2 of 3 folders (Box 44)
- Reports - Iranian Oil Services Limited ca.1958, 3 folders (Box 44)
- Reports - Operating Companies ca.1956, 2 folders (Box 44)
- Supplies ca.1955-1956, 3 folders (Box 44)
- Supplies ca.1956-1957, 5 folders (Box 45)
- Supplies - Arabian American Oil Company ca.1955-1956, 3 folders (Box 45)
- Supplies - Arabian American Oil Company ca.1957-1958, 4 folders (Box 45)
- Supplies - Foreign ca.1956, 5 folders (Box 46)
- Supplies - Iranian Oil Participants,Ltd ca.1954-1955 Jun, 3 folders (Box 46)
- Supplies - Iranian Oil Participants,Ltd ca.1955 Jul-Dec, 5 folders (Box 46)
- Supplies - Iranian Oil Participants,Ltd ca.1956, 4 folders (Box 47)
- Supplies - Iranian Oil Participants,Ltd ca.1957, 3 folders (Box 47)
- Supplies - Iraq Petroleum Co. Ltd ca.1951-1952 Jun, 3 folders (Box 47)
- Supplies - Iraq Petroleum Co. Ltd ca.1952 Jul-Dec, 2 folders (Box 48)
- Supplies - Iraq Petroleum Co. Ltd ca.1953 Jan-Apr, 2 folders (Box 48)
- Supplies - Iraq Petroleum Co. Ltd ca.1953 May-Aug, 3 folders (Box 48)
- Supplies - Iraq Petroleum Co. Ltd ca.1953 Sept-Dec, 2 folders (Box 48)
- Supplies - Iraq Petroleum Co. Ltd ca.1954 Jan-Jun, 3 folders (Box 49)
- Supplies - Iraq Petroleum Co. Ltd ca.1954 Jul-Dec, 4 folders (Box 49)
- Supplies - Iraq Petroleum Co. Ltd ca.1955, 3 of 4 folders (Box 49)
- Supplies - Iraq Petroleum Co. Ltd ca.1955, 4 of 4 folders (Box 50)
- Supplies - Participation And Exploration Corp ca.1955-1956, 3 folders (Box 50)